בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today’s דף daf is קע Kuf Ayin 170.
And we pick up with תנו
רבנן Tanu Rabbanan five—four lines from the bottom on קס״ט עמוד ב׳.
Kuf Samech Tet Amud Bet. So the issue had been that רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said if somebody gives a
שטר shtar of a having bought a field, returns it to the
original owner, then the sale is reversed, and the Rabbis disagree. And
the גמרא Gemara said that the reason of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is, let’s read it, actually, let’s go
six lines from the bottom. אמר רבה באותיות נקנות במסירה קמיפלגי. Amar
Rabbah be'otiyot niknas bimesira kamifligi. The question is, can a שטר shtar
be transferred, meaning and also what the שטר shtar communicates be transferred
just by handing it over? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר אותיות נקנות
במסירה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar otiyot niknas bimesira, it can. The
classic example of this is an IOU. Gloria owes me a thousand
dollars, I give the שטר shtar to David, and now even though
it says that she owes Dov a thousand, since David is holding
it, David now, and I give it to him for the purpose
of transferring the debt, that act transfers the debt and now she
owes David that money.
You can still always מוחל mochel a debt.
Okay, so but that’s the classic debate of אותיות נקנות במסירה otiyot
niknas bimesira and here we’re applying it not to a loan document
but to a sale document. Document said that Gloria sold me her
plot of land on a certain date and a year later or
ten years later I hand over that document to David. So even
though the document says that in 2007 Gloria sold Dov this plot
of land, because I hand it over to David with the intention
of transferring it, he now is the one who owns that plot
of land. Okay, so that’s a new type of a קנין. kinyan.
I mean, we know that land is acquired by a שטר, shtar,
but a שטר shtar written in your name. Okay, so that’s what
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says and therefore if
the שטר shtar is handed back to the original owner, it’s just
like it had been handed to a third party, it transfers the
land back to the original
owner. רבנן סברי אין אותיות נקנות במסירה. Rabbanan savrei ein otiyot niknas
bimesira. No, that is not the way you do a קנין. kinyan.
If it’s a piece of land, you have to write a new
שטר. shtar. If you’re transferring a debt, you give over the original
שטר shtar plus you write a new שטר shtar that says that
the money is now owed to this new party. Okay, so it’s
not enough to just transfer the original document. All right, now we’re
going to see if that way of framing the debate fits with
another debate and we’re going to give about five different reads of
this next debate. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, הבא לידון
בשטר ובחזקה. haba lidon bishtar uvachazaka. There’s
you’re on a piece of land and the question is whether you
should argue your claim based on a שטר shtar or based on
חזקה. chazaka. Now, there are two completely different meanings to the idea
of שטר shtar and חזקה. chazaka. What do you think it means
שטר shtar and חזקה? chazaka? What do you think, what do you
think חזקה chazaka means?
Well, usually it’s חזקת ג׳ שנים, chazakat gimmel shanim, but the only
problem with that is, okay we had that whole thing before, I
mean, you know, if you have a word שטר shtar for—okay,
so one thing is, okay, but okay, but let's just say, one
thing is it means somebody is, I'm claiming, Michael, what are you
doing on my land? And Michael has two things he can bring
to defend himself. One is the חזקה chazaka that he's been on
it for three years, and the other is a שטר shtar that
says I sold it to him. Okay, that I think is how
we would normally interpret this question. Can he produce the חזקה chazaka
or in the presence of the שטר shtar does he actually have
to produce the שטר? shtar? Okay, we're going to get to that,
that's going to be the very last read of this ברייתא braita
that we're going to give. The other read is we're not dealing
with a חזקת ג׳ שנים. chazakat gimmel shanim. What we're dealing with
is the act of taking possession. Everybody agrees that I was trying
to sell this land to Michael. The question is was the sale
finalized or not? Okay, I say we never finalized it, the prices
went up, you're not, you're going to have to pay more, I'm
not going to sell it. Michael said what are you doing, the
sale was finalized. Oh yeah, what did you, what did you buy
it with? Okay, I bought it with a חזקה, chazaka, I went
and I fixed a little thing in the fence. Okay, or I
bought it with a שטר, shtar, here's my שטר. shtar. So then
the question is, so now the שטר shtar and the חזקה chazaka
are not the חזקה chazaka of three years and it's not the
שטר shtar as proof
of ownership, but the act of taking possession. Okay, and which one
should Michael produce? So the question is like, why does it matter?
Either one is good. So let's take a look. But that's the
way most of our interpretations of this ברייתא braita are going to
be, not about שטר shtar and חזקה chazaka as proof of ownership,
but the act of taking possession. הבא לידון בשטר ובחזקה, haba lidon
bishtar uvachazaka, נידון בשטר דברי רבי. nidon bishtar divrei Rabbi. רבי Rabbi
says use the שטר, shtar, prove your ownership or the act of
taking possession was through the שטר. shtar. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
בחזקה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer bechazaka, do the חזקה. chazaka. במאי
קמיפלגי? bemay kamifligi? Now what is that debate about? I mean what
are they talking about and what's the debate about? So כי אתא
רב דימי אמר, ki ata Rav Dimi amar, when Rav Dimi came
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said, באותיות נקנות במסירה קמיפלגי. be'otiyot
niknas bimesira kamifligi. Ah, the question is, did Michael's שטר shtar work
to take possession of the land or does he have to use
a חזקה? chazaka? Why would his שטר shtar not work? Because I
didn't write a שטר shtar in his name. I gave him the
שטר shtar that Gloria gave me when I bought that land from
Gloria ten years ago. So רבי Rabbi says that's fine, that שטר
shtar works, אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiyot niknas bimesira, you can. take possession
through the handing over of the original of the original שטר shtar
even not in that person's name. That's what he says. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל סבר אין אותיות נקנות במסירה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar
ein osiyos niknim b'mesirah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says no, if Michael wants to take possession of that land and
he's not going to write a new שטר, shtar, it can't work
by just handing over the old one, he has to actually do
an act of חזקה. chazakah.
Wait, so I could just give it to me then and a
שטר shtar would work, I wouldn't even need to worry about the
חזקה? chazakah?
One more time? Yeah, if I wanted to write a new שטר,
shtar, everybody would agree, obviously I could.
But forget Gloria, you just give me your, you know, one of
your...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but we have to have an old שטר shtar
in order to have the conversation.
Is he acting in this case as a receipt or or like
some other kind of written note on the back signed by עדים
eidim and other stuff as proof? Because otherwise, אבידה aveidah or etcetera
or נגנב... nignav...
I'm not clear what you're asking. What do you mean אבידה aveidah
or נגנב? nignav?
So, so I told you, you've now got this שטר. shtar. You
said you bought it for me, it's not in your name. Right.
There's no receipt that you bought it for me.
Well, that's the obvious point. The problem with saying that just holding
on, Michael holding onto a שטר shtar that says that Dov bought
a plot of land from Gloria means that he owns it is
like how does he how do we know he didn't pick it
up, I didn't drop it and he didn't pick it up? Okay,
so there's going to be a discussion later on, maybe maybe you
don't, you assume but nevertheless, you assume the person holding it is
the one for whom it testifies the same way if Michael's holding
onto my iPhone, how do you know that I sold it to
him? Maybe I just dropped it and he picked it up? But
nevertheless, possession maybe could makes it his or you know, is a
is a is an indication like is a prima facie evidence that
it's his and maybe the same is true by a שטר. shtar.
But I do understand there's a big difference. The iPhone doesn't say
it's mine, the שטר shtar here says it's in my name and
Gloria's name and not in Michael's name. So there is going to
be an opinion later on that it's not just enough that he
has the שטר, shtar, he have to bring witnesses that I gave
him the שטר shtar with the intent of transferring the land. That
might be. But we have to distinguish between evidence that it's his,
that he got it properly, got what context he got it, and
did the act of giving it over even if we all agree
that I gave it over with that intent, is that a מעשה
קניין? ma'aseh kinyan? Okay, so that's what we're focusing on right now,
but you're right to ask the question: does the fact that he
produces it, does that be evidence that it's his field? Okay, but
we're not asking that right now. Now we are asking is the
act of giving over the שטר shtar work. So רבי Rebbe says
yes, that can work, you don't have to write a new שטר,
shtar, you don't have to do a חזקה, chazakah, just give over
that old שטר shtar and that works. And רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, you need to do a חזקה.
chazakah. So the problem here is, so that's a nice explanation of
that debate, but the problem here is is that is that based
on this, so אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye
said to רב דימי Rav Dimi אם כן im kein if that's
true... no, maybe he said to what do you call it to
to
רבה. Rabbah. אביי Abaye said to רבה Rabbah who said that the
debate about handing back the שטר, shtar, you know, the first thing
we started with, was a debate about אותיות נקנות במסירה. osiyos niknim
b'mesirah. He said אם כן פלוגתא דמר. im kein plugta d'mar. So
this argued on what you said, because you רבה Rabbah said that
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says when you hand
back the שטר, shtar, it goes back to the owner, the field,
cause אותיות נקנות במסירה. osiyos niknim b'mesirah. And this debate of נידון
בשטר ובחזקה nidon b'shtar u'v'chazakah has them saying the reverse, has רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel saying you need to use
the חזקה, chazakah, not the שטר. shtar. So it's the same issue,
but the positions are reversed. So this goes against your way of
explaining that earlier debate. So אמר ליה ותיפלוג amar lei v'tisplog fine,
that argues on my interpretation. What do you want? That's the way
רב דימי Rav Dimi explains that debate. Fine, that's not the way
I would necessarily explain that debate. אמר ליה הכי קאמינא לך amar
lei hachi ka'amina lach here's what I'm saying. מתניתין לא מיתרצא אלא
כדמתרצת מר. masnisin lo misartza ela k'd'misartzat mar. So the first ברייתא,
braisa, when you hand back the שטר shtar does it reverse the
sale of the field? He's אביי Abaye says to רבה, Rabbah, that's
presumably how you explained it, that the reason רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says handing back the שטר shtar transfers back
the sale is אותיות נקנות במסירה. osiyos niknim b'mesirah. So once I'm
going to start with that as my point of departure, how am
I going to read this debate of נידון בשטר ובחזקה? nidon b'shtar
u'v'chazakah? So ואם כן קשיא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אדרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. v'im kein kashya d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel a'd'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
If then this debate of of נידון בשטר ובחזקה nidon b'shtar u'v'chazakah
has the positions reversed, how am I going to do it? Like
one thing's got to change. You've got to change either interpretation of
ברייתא braisa number one or interpretation of ברייתא braisa number two. אלא
אמר אביי הכא במאי עסקינן ela amar Abaye hacha b'mai askinan fine,
רבה Rabbah isn't giving me an answer, I'm going to have to
give a new explanation. I mean, it's רבה Rabbah isn't contradictory, it's
just רבה Rabbah never bothered to explain this second ברייתא. braisa. So
I'm going to have to give a new explanation to this debate
of נידון בשטר ובחזקה nidon b'shtar u'v'chazakah so I don't have רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel argue on himself because on
the case about giving back the שטר, shtar, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says it transfers back the property, that means
אותיות נקנות במסירה, osiyos niknim b'mesirah, and here רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says נידון בחזקה. nidon b'chazakah. So it must
be this second debate is something other than the way that רב
דימי Rav Dimi explained it. Well you could say איפוך eifoch but
we'd rather just give a different context to this debate because this
is very vague what are they talking about. אלא אמר אביי ela
amar Abaye so rather אביי Abaye said the following, הכא במאי עסקינן
hacha b'mai askinan what are we talking about, כגון שנמצא אחד מהם
קרוב ופסול. k'gon shenimtza echad meihem karov u'pasul. One of them, meaning,
okay, again, we're debate did I is the... Sale of the field
I sold to Michael final. And the question is, can we use
the שטר? shtar? So the first way of framing the debate is,
can we use the שטר shtar because it was not a new
שטר shtar in Michael's name, it was the old שטר shtar with
from Gloria. Okay, we that was one read of it. The next
read of it is, can we use the שטר shtar because the
problem with the שטר shtar is is that it's got a פסול
pasul witness signed on it. Okay, we wrote a new שטר shtar
in Michael's name, but it's got a פסול pasul witness signed on
it.
So how would I think I could use the שטר? shtar?
So let's take a look. He says, אחד מהם קרוב או פסול,
echad mehem karov o pasul, במפלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבי אלעזר קמיפלגי. bemiflogta
d'rabbi meir v'rabbi elazar kamiflegi. Is it one of them that's karov
or pasul or you have more? You have well what we're going
to find out is you only have two witnesses signed, but you
have two witnesses who observed the
handing over of the שטר. shtar.
And the debate is, can you go by the witnesses who observed
rather than the witnesses who signed? עדי מסירה edei mesirah versus עדי
חתימה, edei chatimah, a long-standing debate. Okay, so this is a new
שטר shtar though? Yes, exactly, new אוקימתא. ukimta. אוקימתא ukimta number one
was the debate was when I handed over Gloria's שטר, shtar, did
Michael own it? But that we said doesn't work with the way
we explained the other ברייתא, braita, the positions were reversed. So now
we're saying the question is does it work for Michael to take
possession of the field with the new שטר shtar that I wrote
in his name that had a פסול pasul witness signed on but
had כשר kasher witnesses witnessing the handing over of the שטר? shtar?
Okay, so that's a different אוקימתא ukimta of this ברייתא, braita, new
שטר shtar in Michael's name with a פסול pasul witness signed on.
אלא אמר אביי, ella amar abaye, so Abaye said where are we?
הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון
שנמצא אחד מהן קרוב או פסול. kegon shenimtza echad mehen karov o
pasul. ובמפלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבי אלעזר קמיפלגי. ubemiflogta d'rabbi meir v'rabbi elazar
kamiflegi. The debate is the same debate of Rabbi Meir and Rabbi
Elazar. רבי סבר לה כרבי אלעזר, rabbi savar lah k'rabbi elazar, Rabbi
holds like Rabbi Elazar דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. d'amar edei mesirah karti.
So Rabbi who says נידון בשטר nidon beshtar says you can use
the שטר shtar even though the witnesses signed are not good because
the witnesses who saw the handing over are good and they can
be the real witnesses of the שטר. shtar. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
סבר לה כרבי מאיר rabban shimon ben gamliel savar lah k'rabbi meir
דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי d'amar edei chatimah karti and Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says no, נידון בחזקה, nidon behazakah, Michael's שטר shtar doesn't work
to take possession, he has to do a חזקה hazakah because the
only witnesses you pay attention to are the ones signed on the
שטר shtar and they're no good. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says
one minute, that can't be the case. דאמר רבי אבא, d'amar rabbi
abba, but don't we know that Rabbi Abba says מודה היה רבי
אלעזר במזויף מתוכו שפסול, modeh hayah rabbi elazar bimzuyat mitocho shepasul, that
Rabbi Elazar would agree that even though he says you can go
by the עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, that's if there's nothing written in
the שטר shtar that's bad. Meaning, what they can do is they
can fill in a gap. The absence of written עדים edim on
the שטר shtar is supplemented or the role of עדים edim in
the שטר shtar should be done by the עדים edim that witness
it. Okay, but if you have something wrong in the שטר, shtar,
a פסול עד, pasul ed, that invalidates the שטר shtar and that
you can't ignore the signed witnesses. So a פסול עד pasul ed
would actually invalidate the שטר. shtar. So nobody would say a שטר
shtar like this would be okay. Okay, אלא אמר רבי אבינא ella
amar rabbi avina הכל מודים שאם כתב בו הוסקקנו לעדותן של עדים
ונמצאת עדותן מזויפת שהוא פסול hakol modim she'im katav bo huskaknu l'edutan
shel edim venimtzeit edutan mezuyefet shehu pasul כרבי אבא. k'rabbi abba. Everybody
agrees that basically, you know, that Rabbi Abba is right, that if
you write in the שטר shtar that, you know, oh, you know,
the עדים edim who signed the שטר shtar whatever are פסול, pasul,
I don't know why you'd explicitly write it in the שטר shtar
or whatever or but it means let's say you didn't write it
or basically, you know, that the witnesses who were the עדי מסירה
edei mesirah after they saw it handing over or something like, you
know, put into the שטר shtar that the עדים edim who actually
signed the שטר shtar were no good, then it would be no
good even though you had עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, that would not
help you. Okay, fine. לא נחלקו אלא בשטר שאין עליו עדים כלל.
lo nechelku ella beshtar she'ein alav edim klal. So here's the debate.
Here's the way of explaining what is the debate whether the שטר
shtar would work or do you need to do a חזקה. hazakah.
So rather than saying the שטר shtar has a bad עד, ed,
we'll say the שטר shtar just doesn't have any עדים edim on
it. All right, that's an easier way of now explaining tapping into
the classic debate of עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, עדי חתימה. edei chatimah.
דרבי סבר לה כרבי אלעזר rabbi savar lah k'rabbi elazar דאמר עדי
מסירה כרתי, d'amar edei mesirah karti, so this שטר shtar can work
because there were עדי מסירה. edei mesirah. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר
לה כרבי מאיר דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי. v'rabban shimon ben gamliel savar
lah k'rabbi meir d'amar edei chatimah karti. Okay, עדי חתימה. edei chatimah.
So again, you've got this debate, right? I mean, basically because it
is so vague, it allows us to plug in many different possibilities,
okay, although it's not until the end that we're going to do
what is probably the פשט, pshat, which is it's a question about
proof, not about the מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. But basically you've got
Rabbi saying שטר shtar and Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel saying חזקה. hazakah.
So what is the problem? And now first here, we're going to
assume the whole first range of possibilities here are all going to
say we're all talking about basically about שטר shtar and חזקה hazakah
for the מעשה קנין, maaseh kinyan, for the מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan.
Okay, so those are going to be the whole first range of
possibilities. And now within that, we have a couple of different ways
of understanding it. Okay, we have a case we're handing over an
old שטר, shtar, handing over an old שטר shtar in somebody else's
name, that's possibility number one and he says it works because of
אותיות נקנות במסירה, otiot niknot bemesirah, meaning handing over an old שטר
shtar and he says it does work. He says it doesn't work.
Possibility number two is נמצא אחד קרוב או פסול. nimtza echad karov
oh pasul. Okay, he says it works because עדי מסירה. edei mesirah.
He says it doesn't work because עדי חתימה. edei chatimah. And then
we actually say, actually this case everybody would say it doesn't work
because it's מזויף מתוכו, mizuyaph mitocho, so basically אין עליו עדים. ein
alav edim. Okay, and Rebbe says it works because again עדי מסירה
edei mesirah and he says it doesn't work because you need עדי
חתימה. edei chatimah. Okay, but we have all these different possibilities of
why should the שטר shtar be no good. So one possibility, or
why should there be a debate about the שטר. shtar. One is
because it's an old שטר, shtar, okay, that's why there's a debate,
meaning it was the original שטר, shtar, not in this person's name.
And the other right now is אין עליו עדים ein alav edim
because it's and therefore the question is can you use עדי מסירה.
edei mesirah. We have to create a way if they're debating about
using a שטר shtar for the מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, so we're
going to find ways in which to say they would be debating
the validity of the שטר. shtar. Okay, and right now we have
these two ways: either it's an old שטר shtar and that's why
maybe it's not valid, meaning it was written in somebody else's name,
the original person, or it doesn't have witnesses and it's a question
of עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, עדי חתימה. edei chatimah. Yeah, Resh Lakish
calls that תיקון עולם tikkun olam that a גט אשה, get isha,
the עדים... edim... well according to if you say עדי מסירה... edei
mesirah... exactly I was going to clarify that's only one position. Yeah
exactly. So even one of these positions is that even if the
שטר shtar itself is invalid, just witnessing the handing over validates it?
One more time. Is one of the positions that even if the
שטר shtar itself is invalid? No, it doesn't have any witnesses. No,
but the point is that's not invalid. Oh, עדי מסירה edei mesirah
means it's not invalid, it means it doesn't have עדים. edim. The
absence of עדים edim is satisfied by the presence of witnesses who
are there when it's handed over. They were there. That's what עדי
מסירה edei mesirah means. They were there when it was handed over.
Okay, it doesn't mean anything. No one knows what, you know, it
could have been made up. Yeah, but then the witnesses come and
testify to the fact that that happened. Right, the problem is that
then the שטר shtar doesn't serve as evidence. It only serves as
a vehicle for doing the קנין. kinyan. Like a חזקה chazakah in
front of עדים. edim. It's not the same as being able to
prove that it's yours. It's just taking possession. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, אי בעית אימא, ee ba'it eimah, here's
possibility number I don't know three or four about whether the שטר
shtar would be good. מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו? modeh b'shtar shektavo
tzarich lekayamo? Remember that? If somebody admits that the שטר shtar is
written but he says it's not valid for another reason, do you
need to do a קיום? kiyuum? Wait what? So basically, I gave,
so basically Michael has this שטר, shtar, okay, and it says that
he bought the field. And I say,
you know what, I say look,
it's true I wrote the שטר, shtar, I had witnesses sign it,
but I never gave it over. We hadn't finalized the deal. It
slipped out of my pocket or I left it on the table.
Michael picked it up and he never really did a קנין kinyan
on it and we never really did the קנין. kinyan. Okay, so
does that work? Do we think that that's a valid שטר? shtar?
Now we're moving a little from קנין kinyan to proof, okay, but
the question is because I mean because, so does, and the real
question is not whether if Michael can validate the signatures, everybody would
agree it's his. The question is does he need to validate the
signatures because I admitted that it was a legitimately signed document. מודה
בשטר שכתבו, modeh b'shtar shektavo, I admitted that. Okay, I'm not claiming
it's a forgery. I'm just saying you gave it to me, doesn't
matter, but I'm admitting that the signatures are good. So the question
here is that so I do have a מיגו, migo, I מיגו
migo I could challenge the witnesses, but that's exactly the position. מודה
בשטר שכתבו אינו צריך לקיימו modeh b'shtar shektavo eino tzarich lekayamo means
even though I could have had a מיגו, migo, even though I
could have claimed that the witnesses are no good and through that
prevented him from using it until he validated them, since I'm right
now claiming that, admitting, conceding that the witnesses were a properly signed
שטר, shtar, not a properly handed over שטר, shtar, but a properly
signed שטר, shtar, Michael has no need to validate the witnesses.
But I'm saying that what? You actually gave it to me? Okay,
because if I said I found it then,
no no no, you say you gave it to me, I'm claiming
you found it. But I'm admitting that it was a properly signed
שטר. shtar. So the idea here is we don't, according to the
principle of מודה בשטר שכתבו אינו צריך לקיימו, modeh b'shtar shektavo eino
tzarich lekayamo, is because we say you know why we don't have
מיגו? migo? Here's the best way I have to explain this. The
reason we ignore the normal claim of מיגו migo is because fundamentally
a שטר shtar doesn't need to have the witnesses validated. חז״ל Chazal
only required it to be validated if its validity was challenged. If
the original owner was saying those are forged signatures or you whatever
I never did this, that creates a, that invalidates the שטר shtar
and requires the signatures to be validated before the שטר shtar can
be used. But in the absence of a challenge, the שטר shtar
is valid just by the signatures.
That's the תיקון. tikkun. So requiring the, right? That must be the
תיקון עולם tikkun olam as it were...
No no you're mixing it up, I don't want to... that's a
different תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, let's not go there right now. That's
the תיקון... tikkun... whatever, let's bracket that. Okay, anyway, but the... But
the point is, is that, so according to that approach, Michael, and
according to that approach, even though I have a מיגו, migo, the
מיגו migo doesn't mean anything. Right now it's signed witnesses that don't
need validation because they're not being challenged. So signed witnesses that don't
need validation and Michael's holding the שטר shtar as evidence that it's
his. Okay, and my claim that he picked it up and he
stole it or whatever is meaningless. He's holding on to a valid
שטר. shtar.
Okay. Wait, would it work that way also since we're comparing this
to the כתובות Kesubos in some places? Yeah, I mean, wait, what?
As long as the husband is not claiming, no, no, no, I'm
using found it not to say that, I'm sorry if that's confusing
you. I'm using that to say that's my claim. If you actually
found, if Michael actually found it and I didn't give it to
him it wouldn't be good, the same is true about a גט.
get. Michael, I'm just using it to explain how come I'm admitting
it was validly signed but I'm still saying that he doesn't own
the field. 'Cause I'm claiming I never gave it to him. I
dropped it and he found it. Michael is saying I'm a liar.
I gave it to him, okay, and I gave it to him
properly. Okay, so so that's why even if what I'm saying is
correct, he doesn't own the field. But he's saying that I'm lying
and he's saying he got it properly, and the question is, does
he need to validate the signatures to back up his claim? Okay,
and that's a debate.
Which is basically hanging on other מחלוקות. machlokos. Exactly.
Well, we have a vague debate here. Okay, and so the best
thing we can do is try to tap it into other things
that we know, other debates that we know about. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So, רבי סבר מודה בשטר שכתבו אינו
צריך לקיימו Rebbi savar modeh bi-shtar she-kesavo eino tzarich le-kaymo that the
שטר shtar can be used and now we're shifting a little from
a מעשה קנין maaseh kinyan to a proof, because the question is
Michael's proving that he took possession of the field and he says
that he can use the שטר, shtar, ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר
צריך לקיימו. ve-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar tzarich le-kaymo. No, okay, so
according to this, this is actually now more about a different category.
I don't know if we're going to double back, okay, but this
is like version one which is doesn't work as a מעשה קנין.
maaseh kinyan. And now we're going to get a different way of
understanding it, not does it work as a מעשה קנין maaseh kinyan
but שטר shtar and חזקה, chazakah, חזקה chazakah here would be ג'
שנים gimmel shanim presumably, right, as proof. Okay, so does the שטר
shtar work, so one way is the שטר shtar is אינו מקוים,
eino mekuyam, but the other side is admitting about that it's okay.
So רבי Rebbi says it's good, מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh bi-shtar she-kesavo,
מודה בשטר שכתבו modeh bi-shtar she-kesavo אינו צריך לקיימו, eino tzarich le-kaymo,
and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is
saying it's no good, צריך לקיימו. tzarich le-kaymo. It's really not that
it's no good, it's no good as long as you haven't been
מקיים mekayem it. Once you're מקיים mekayem it the שטר shtar will
be good, okay. So according to this now, you see how now
we're in a debate of not was it a good מעשה קנין,
maaseh kinyan, but does it prove that Michael owns it? Okay, you
can't leave, you have to take possession of the field. Okay, does
it prove that Michael owns it? So according to this, the question
is, can it prove that Michael owns it if it's not validated?
But I admit that it was properly signed. I don't admit that
he properly has it, okay, but I admit it was properly signed.
So רבי Rebbi says go ahead
and use the שטר, shtar, and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, he can't
use the שטר shtar because I have a מיגו, migo, I could
have claimed that it was a forgery. As long as it's not
מקוים mekuyam he can't use the שטר. shtar. So according to the
position of אינו צריך לקיימו, eino tzarich le-kaymo, right, because the original
guy admits that it was a valid שטר, shtar, it's got legal
force, the guy's holding on to the field, and it's really המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah. If he wants to claim
a different claim, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah, the
other guy actually has a שטר shtar that testifies that it's his.
Right, but there's a challenge not to the שטר. shtar. Challenge, well,
it is a challenge to the שטר's shtar validity, not to whether
it was forged or not, but I claim I never gave him
the שטר. shtar. But his holding on to the שטר, shtar, to
a שטר shtar with proper signed witnesses, and witnesses that haven't been
challenged is a test, that שטר shtar now is testifying that it's
his field. So that's how it works. So I'm like, it's like
he brought witnesses to court and the witnesses were accepted in court
and I said the witnesses were liars or whatever, not liars or
whatever. Anyway, right now, if the שטר shtar doesn't need קיום, kiyum,
the reason he wins is because he has a valid שטר shtar
testifying that it's his field. Yeah, but there's a time gap between
the signature and the delivery. Right, so validating the signatures would seem
to be irrelevant, that's not the issue that's in dispute. What do
you mean? If everybody agrees that the signatures were valid, right, but
the issue is was it delivered to the buyer. Right, exactly. קיום
kiyum of the signatures doesn't have anything to do with... The signature,
right, what you're saying is the signatures don't prove what happened after
it was signed. That's true about a גט get too. How come?
It's true about any שטר. shtar. Any שטר shtar is, if the
event of the giving over, actually you could say even if it
is a second later, the witnesses if they... what happened in the
gap between the signing of the גט Get and the giving to
the woman. So part of the חידוש Chidush of a שטר Shtar
is that the person who is holding the שטר Shtar and for
whom the שטר Shtar is telling the narrative about, right? And sort
of that sort of creates, you know, fills in the gap, meaning
not circumstantially, it's almost like the mechanism of a שטר Shtar is
that if I'm holding a שטר Shtar that says that Gloria, you
know, borrowed a thousand dollars from me or sold me her field,
so and then, and that what the הלכתי Halachic meaning of my
holding it is, is that they are testifying to that reality, even
though from a practical standpoint we don't know, all we know is
witnesses signed it and then a certain time later I'm holding onto
it. But what it's perceived of is I've got a narrative in
a שטר, Shtar, I am producing the שטר Shtar in בית דין
Beit Din so that is seen to testify to the facts that
are in it. But you're right, I mean as a fact of
actual question of is there an is there actual evidence, meaning not
a formal proof, but evidence that, you know, that I that this
happened? No. A lot of you know, it could have been A,
could have been forged, B, could have been signed and not delivered,
right? But הלכתית, Halachically, it's testifying to what it what it says.
Now עדי מסירה Eidie Mesirah comes to cover... Well, עדי מסירה Eidie
Mesirah would cover that gap. It covers... That's correct, that's if you
demand עדי מסירה, Eidie Mesirah, that is correct. That covers that position.
But even with עדי מסירה, Eidie Mesirah, according to some opinions, you
need עדי מסירה Eidie Mesirah to make it valid, but the שטר
Shtar still works as your תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam before, the שטר
Shtar still works as evidence, so even with עדי מסירה, Eidie Mesirah,
the evidence doesn't necessarily require that the עדי מסירה Eidie Mesirah be
brought to court. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואיפכא שמיע להו, Va'ipcha shmiah lehu, how can you say this debate
is about מודה בשטר שכתבו, Modeh Beshtar Shekatavo, we know that רבי
Rebbe and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hold the
opposite positions. דתניא: Detanya: שנים אוחזין בשטר. Shnayim Achuzin Beshtar. Two people
are holding onto a שטר. Shtar. מלווה Malveh אומר Omer שלי הוא.
Sheli Hu. The lender says it's mine, it says that ראובן Reuven
owes me ten thousand dollars and it's still mine, ונפל ממני, Venafal
Mimeni, it fell from me, ומצאתו, Umetzato, and he the לווה Loveh
found it and thinks he's going to get out of paying me.
ולווה Veloveh אומר Omer שלך הוא ופרעתי לך. Shelach Hu Uparati Lach.
Yes, it was yours, but I paid you and it fell from
me and I totally paid up the שטר. Shtar. So, יתקיים השטר
בחותמיו Itkayeim Hashtar Bechosamav דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbe. רבי Rebbe says you've
got to validate the signatures. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel אומר יחלקו, Omer Yachloku, you split it. Now, split it you
understand, it's like two people holding onto a טלית. Tallis. Okay, but
what is the idea of validating the signatures? Who would win? It
would sound like once you've validated the signatures, we would give it
fully to the מלווה, Malveh, the מלווה Malveh would, you know, collect
full. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואבינא בה, Va'avina Bah, we asked
on this, וליתי ד-רבי הדתנן, Veleitei deRebbe Hadatnan, does רבי Rebbe not
hold of this general principle of שנים אוחזין בטלית זה אומר אני
מצאתיה וזה אומר אני מצאתיה? Shnayim Achuzin Betallis Zeh Omer Ani Mtzativ
Vezeh Omer Ani Mtzativ? This one says I found it, this one
says I found it. זה ישבע שאין לו בה פחות מחציה וזה
ישבע שאין לו בה פחות מחציה ויחלקו. Zeh Yishava She'ein Lo Bo
Pachot Mechatzya Vezeh Yishava She'ein Lo Bo Pachot Mechatzya Veyachloku. Each one
swears they don't have less than half and you divide it. Meaning
even if you validated the signatures, how could you say why how
could you give it to the מלווה? Malveh? The לווה's Loveh holding
onto half of it. So, ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, so רבא Rava
said to explain this debate, so אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
במקויים, Bimkuyam, if the שטר Shtar was validated and the לווה Loveh
and the מלווה Malveh were yanking it and holding onto it, דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דיחלקו. Dechulya Alma Lo Pligi Deyachloku. Everybody agrees you
split it, it's just like a טלית Tallis and you pay half
the debt. כי פליגי בשאינו מקויים. Ki Pligi B'she'eino Mekuyam. That it's
not מקויים. Mekuyam. רבי סבר מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו. Rabbi savar
modeh beshtar she-katvo tzarich lekaymo. That that you have to... So basically
what's happening, this is a classic מודה בשטר שכתבו, Modeh Beshtar Shekatavo,
the לווה's Loveh saying the yes, I concede that it's a valid
שטר, Shtar, but I paid it up. Meaning it's no longer active,
it's
been deactivated, but it was valid, I'm conceding that. Okay? And here
we are we're yanking it, right? And I'm the לווה. Loveh. So
the question is like this: If the שטר Shtar is agreed to
be valid, it's מקויים Mekuyam or it's validated or whatever, everybody agrees
יחלקו. Yachloku. But right now it hasn't been validated. But I the
לווה Loveh who am saying
I paid it up, say that it's no longer effective, but I'm
admitting that it doesn't
need
קיום, Kiyum, I'm admitting that they were properly signed. So, if we
say that
it doesn't need קיום, Kiyum, the פסק Psak will be יחלקו, Yachloku,
right? Because you have a totally valid שטר Shtar here יחלקו, Yachloku,
it's just like it's been מקויים. Mekuyam. But if we say that
until it's been מקויים Mekuyam it's worthless, then until the מלווה Malveh
gets it validated, he's not even going to get his half. He's
going to get nothing. People get this scenario? Yeah? Okay, so, right
here, maybe I'll draw a picture. It allows me to draw an
action shot. Okay. Here's the שטר. Shtar. Okay, and there's ten thousand
dollars in the שטר Shtar and they're arguing, okay? That's the מלווה
Malveh and that's the לווה. Loveh. So if it's a valid
שטר, Shtar, if it's מקויים, Mekuyam, then you split it, okay? And
basically he's still entitled to collect five thousand dollars. Okay, but if
it's אינו מקויים, Eino Mekuyam, so if it's אינו מקויים... Eino Mekuyam...
worthless right now if it's אינו מקוים. eino mekuyam.
So if you say even אינו מקוים, eino mekuyam, it still is
of
completely valid שטר, shtar, because the לוה loveh is admitting that it
was actually properly signed, so then the פסק psak would be יחלוקו.
yachloku. But if you say if it's אינו מקוים eino mekuyam it's
worthless until it's get
מקיים mikayem even with the לוה loveh admitting to it,
then the מלוה malveh gets zero until he actually is מקיים mikayem
it.
To be מקיים mikayem it you have to get the עדים. edim.
You have to get witnesses to testify to the signatures. Right. Okay.
So במקוים דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דיחלוקו, bimkuyam dekulei alma lo peligi
de-yachloku, you split it. כי פליגי, ki peligi, what do they debate?
בשאינו מקוים. bechshe-eino mekuyam. רבי Rebbe סבר Savar מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך
לקיימו. Modeh Beshtar Shekatavo Tzarich Lekaymo. Rabbi says you have to be
מקיים mikayem it, even though the לוה loveh admits it was properly
signed, it's a worthless שטר shtar because the לוה loveh is claiming
he paid it. So the effect of what the לוה loveh is
saying is that you can't collect. So even though the לוה loveh
admits it was signed, the מלוה malveh can't use it at all
until he's מקיים mikayem it. Where were we? צריך לקיימו ואם מקוים
לגבי פלגא, tzarich lekaymo ve'im mekuyam lagabei palga, if he is מקיים
mikayem it, he gets half, ולא, velo, and if he doesn't מקיים
mikayem it, חספא בעלמא, chaspa be-alma, it's like a piece of pottery.
So when Rabbi says, you know, יקיים שטר בחותמיו, yekayem shtar b'chosmo,
it means you got to do קיום kiyum before you can get
your half. You as the מלוה malveh could get up to half
of this שטר, shtar, but until you're מקיים mikayem it you get
zero. יקיים שטר בחותמיו yekayem shtar b'chosmo and then you'll get your
half. Okay. And רבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר מודה בשטר שכתבו אין
צריך לקיימו ויחלוקו Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar modeh beshtar she-katvo ein
tzarich lekaymo ve-yachloku and split it. Okay. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, even without מקוים mekuyam it's split.
So here, it's the flip of what you've got here. Here Rabbi
says use the שטר, shtar, and we said that's because of מודה
בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו. modeh beshtar she-katvo tzarich lekaymo. And here Rabbi
is saying that it's worthless until you do קיום. kiyum. Right? And
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is split. Here רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is saying you can't use
the שטר, shtar, use חזקה. chazaka. And here רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is saying the שטר shtar is good and
split it. Okay, so they've switched their positions. So the first answer
is איפוך, ipuch, fine, just reverse them. Okay, it doesn't clear which
one we're reversing.
Fine, it's the same debate,
but we'll just reverse it so they're saying the same thing. ואיבעית
אימא ve-iba'it eima and if you want לעולם לא תיפוך
אלא הכא דלברר קמיפלגי.
le'olam lo teipoch
ela
hacha de-le-varer kamipalgi.
So now we get to the I don't know, what are we,
fourth or fifth final explanation? Okay, so we had two explanations that
survived in terms of this as a קנין, kinyan, okay? Does the
שטר shtar work because it's the handing over of an old שטר?
shtar? That's אותיות נקנות במסירה. osiyos niknos bemesira. Or does the שטר
shtar work because it's no עדים? edim? That's עדי מסירה כרתי. edei
mesira karsi. That's one way of debating it. Okay, or now we're
actually whether the שטר shtar functions as proof. So one question is
does it function as proof, it's not מקוים. mekuyam. מודה בשטר שכתבו,
modeh beshtar she-katvo, but the other guy admits that it was written,
just that it wasn't handed over. Okay, so that's the debate of
מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו. modeh beshtar she-katvo tzarich lekaymo. That's that
debate. According to all these debates until now, the חזקה chazaka definitely
works, the question is does the שטר shtar work? Okay? Yes? Yeah.
That's the question, is the שטר shtar valid? Now what we're going
to do is we're going to flip it. And we're going to
say that the question is which one to use. I have a
חזקה chazaka and a שטר shtar and can I use my חזקה
chazaka and it says, or you know, or I must use the
שטר, shtar, is what Rabbi is going to say, and I can
use the חזקה. chazaka. So according to all of these, the question
was is the שטר shtar valid? Right? According to all of these
explanations, is the שטר shtar valid? There was a problem with the
שטר shtar and we gave different types of problems with the שטר.
shtar. Here the question is I claim I have a valid שטר
shtar and I also have a חזקת ג' שנים. chazaka of gimmel
shanim. And Rabbi says you must use your שטר. shtar. Once you're
claiming you have a better proof, a שטר, shtar, חזקה chazaka is
only a substitute for a שטר. shtar. Remember going all the way
back? וחזקת ג' שנים ve-chazaka of gimmel shanim is because I could
say I lost my שטר. shtar. But the better thing is the
direct testimony provided by the שטר. shtar. So Rabbi here says, so
until here the question was is the שטר shtar valid? Here the
question is, must you use your שטר shtar if you claim you
have it? Rabbi says you must and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says you can always just use your חזקה. chazaka.
Okay, so that's where we are now. Dov, we were missing you.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay. אלא הכא דלברר קמיפלגי.
ela hacha delevarer kamipalgi. The question is do you have to prove
your case if you have better evidence? Do you have to bring
the better evidence or is it okay to bring the sufficient evidence
even if it's not the best evidence? Okay? כי הא דרבי יצחק
בר יוסף, ki ha de-Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef, like that of רבי
יצחק בר יוסף. Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef. הוה מסיק ביה זוזי ברבי
אבהו hava masik bei zuzei be-Rabbi Avahu before we get to the
case, the question is I say, I claim I've got a שטר
shtar and I've got חזקת ג' שנים. chazakas gimmel shanim. So רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you want to just
use your חזקה, chazaka, be my guest, that's a completely sufficient proof
that it's yours. Rabbi says if you've told us you have better
evidence, you have to. Even though חזקה chazaka normally would suffice, it's
almost like you know sometimes the less you say the better, now
that you've told us you have better evidence, you're required to produce
it. Okay, and you're required to produce the שטר. shtar. Okay, now
the question, interesting question is going to be... "What? How are they
reading that?" נידון בשאר בחזקה, Nidom beshar bachazaka, it's going back to
this thing. Yeah, it's נידון בשאר בחזקה. Nidom beshar bachazaka. No, we're
not dealing with this read here, but the מקוים. mekuyam. So רבי
Rebi says נידון בשאר, Nidom beshar, right, you have to go ahead
and once you've told us you have a שטר, shtar, you have
to produce it. Okay, so that the question is going to be,
let's say you can't produce it. What would be the story בדיעבד?
bedi'eved? But at least לכתחילה, lichatchila, רבי Rebi demands that if you
told us that there's a שטר, shtar, we don't want your חזקה
chazaka right now, we want the שטר shtar if you told us
there's a שטר. shtar. Okay. And now we're going to have a
case to illustrate it. כי הא דרבי יצחק בר יוסף. Ki had
de'Rebbi Yitzchak bar Yosef. רבי יצחק בר יוסף הוי מסיק בזוזי ברבי
אבא. Rebi Yitzchak bar Yosef havai masik beizuzei beRebbi Abba. So he
lent money to רבי אבא. Rebi Abba. אתא לקמיה דרבי יצחק נפחא.
Ata lekamei de'Rebbi Yitzchak Nafcha. So he said, "רבי אבא, Rebi Abba,
where's my money?" אמר פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני. Amar peraticha bifnei ploni
uploni. I paid you up. Now there's no שטר shtar in this
case. He just says "I lent you a thousand dollars" and he
says "Yes, I admit that you lent me a thousand dollars, or
maybe there are עדים edim that you lent me a thousand dollars,
but I paid you up in front of ראובן Reuven and שמעון."
Shimon. Okay. So אמר ליה amar lei רבי יצחק, Rebi Yitzchak, יבוא
פלוני ופלוני ויעידו. yavo ploni uploni veye'eidu. Let them come and testify
that you paid them up. Now the normal הלכה halacha is that
he didn't have to say "I paid you up in front of
ראובן Reuven and שמעון." Shimon. The principle is that המלווה חבירו בעדים
אין צריך לפורעו בעדים. hamalveh chaveiro be'edim ein tzarich lefar'o be'edim. In
the absence of a שטר, shtar, it's really stupid of me to
lend you money in the absence of a שטר, shtar, because then
you are believed to say you paid me up, and you don't
have to bring any supporting evidence. So this רבי אבא Rebi Abba
could have basically said "I paid him up" and the case would
have been over. It would have been over. No, okay, but I
mean probably a שבועת היסת מדרבנן, shvuas hesses miderabbanan, but whatever, but
in principle, no. Okay, but he offered a little bit more information
and he actually said, he could have just said "I paid you
up," case would have been over. But he said "I paid you
up in front of ראובן Reuven and שמעון." Shimon. So now the
דיין dayyan is saying, רבי יצחק Rebi Yitzchak is saying, "Okay, have
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon come if you want to win the
case." So he says, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back
to him, אי לא אתו לא מהימנא? i lo asu lo meheimna?
If they don't come, would I not be believed? והקיימא לן, veha'kayma
lan, we rule, המלווה חבירו בעדים אינו צריך לפורעו בעדים. hamalveh chaveiro
be'edim eino tzarich lefar'o be'edim. I didn't need to pay up in
front of witnesses. My claim that I paid up would have sufficed.
So just because I admitted that I paid up in front of
witnesses, what, I'm not going to be, you know, if they can't
come, you know, that's not going to be sufficient? So אמר ליה,
amar lei, רבי יצחק נפחא Rebi Yitzchak Nafcha said back to him,
אנא בהאי שמעתא דמר סבירא לי. ana beha'i shmaitsa demar sevir li.
You know what? I'm just פוסקין paskin the way you פוסקין. paskin.
You, רבי אבא, Rebi Abba, פוסקין. paskin. Why? דאמר רבי אבא אמר
רב אדא בר אבא. de'amar Rebi Abba amar Rav Adda bar Abba.
So רבי אבא Rebi Abba has been talking a little too much.
He talked too much in this court case, and he talked too
much in this פסק. psak. And here's what he said in this
פסק. psak. אמר רב האומר לחבירו פרעתיך בפני פלוני ופלוני צריך שיבוא
פלוני ופלוני ויעידו, Amar Rav ha'omer lechaveiro peraticha bifnei ploni uploni tzarich
yavo ploni uploni veye'eidu, which is bizarre. He פוסקינד paskined exactly this
case. If you admitted that you were in front of two witnesses,
they have to come and testify, which makes it very strange. How
come he was so shocked that this was what was being פוסקינד
paskined for him if he himself directly פוסקינד paskined this case? Anyway,
אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him, one minute,
והאמר רב גידל אמר רב הלכה כדברי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. veha'amar
Rav Gidel amar Rav halacha kedivrei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. But we
rule, presumably we're now buying into this read of the debate, and
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. And
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you can use
a חזקה. chazaka. You don't need to use the better שטר. shtar.
Okay, I don't exactly get why how that contradicts the fact of
the פסק psak a minute ago that they have to come and
testify. But anyway, we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, you don't need the better evidence. What's the חזקה chazaka
here in this case? Well, the חזקה chazaka is here his claim
that he paid up. That suffices. You don't need the better evidence
that the witnesses are there. So he says, אמר ליה, amar lei,
הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל ואף רבי, halacha keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel
ve'af Rebi, and even רבי Rebi who says that you need to
use the שטר, shtar, לא אמר אלא לברר. lo amar ela levarer.
He only said it as a meaning the best way to read
this, the way תוספות Tosfos reads this, which is clearly the best
way to read this is, רבי Rebi only said it לכתחילה. lichatchila.
רבי Rebi said not that yes, if you claim you have a
שטר shtar you have to produce it, but if you can't produce
it at the end of the day, the חזקה chazaka will suffice.
It's just something that we demand לכתחילה. lichatchila. We want all the
evidence to be brought in front of us. Okay, but just because
we're asking and demanding it, doesn't mean that if you can't bring
it you're going to lose your case. Alright, which makes sense. אמר
ליה, amar lei, אנא נמי לברר קאמינא. ana nami levarer ka'amina. So
רבי יצחק נפחא Rebi Yitzchak Nafcha said back, yeah, that's also what
I said. When I said יבוא פלוני ופלוני ויעידו, yavo ploni uploni
veye'eidu, I didn't mean you would lose your case if you couldn't
produce them. I mean you're telling us that they were there, before
I פוסקין paskin let them come and testify. Maybe they'll come and
testify and we'll find out more information. I never said that if
you can't produce them you would lose. What I said was that
you have to produce them. Okay. And if he doesn't produce them?
And if he... If you don't produce them, so the way תוספות
Tosafot reads it is, okay, if at the end of the day
you can't produce them, you'll still win. This is only a לכתחילה
lechatchila requirement. Now, right, now the רשב״ם Rashbam disagrees. The רשב״ם Rashbam
actually says that if you can't produce them בדיעבד bedieved you'll lose.
Okay, but it sounds like the tone of the גמרא Gemara was
you only required it לברר levarrer and I'm also only asking for
it for the purpose of לברר. levarrer. So the way תוספות Tosafot
reads that is, it's only a לכתחילה lechatchila requirement. You, even according
to רבי, Rebbi, all רבי Rebbi is saying is is that when
you tell us about it, we're going to demand to see it
before we can finish the case. If for some reason, because we
want to see all the evidence in front of us, if for
some reason it can't be produced then, okay, in the end of
the day you still have your חזקה, chazaka, in the end of
the day you still have your claim that you paid up. But
Dov is there sitting there with his arms crossed and a skeptical
air about him because he thinks that the point that if we're
going to demand it לכתחילה lechatchila and we're going to say we
want it and the inability to produce it would raise questions about
your veracity and would raise would make us question your entire claim.
So that's anyway, that's the way the רשב״ם Rashbam says. In the
end the רשב״ם Rashbam says אי הכי נמי in hachi nami that
if you can't prove it, then if you can't bring it, you
are going to lose. But it sounded from the exchange that he
was conceding like don't worry you're going to win anyway, you know,
I just want to see the witnesses. Yes? You sure set up
the correlation between the שטר shtar and the witnesses here? You've got
the שטר shtar here in... Yeah here in this case his claim
that he paid equals the חזקה chazaka and the שטר shtar equals
the witnesses and the claim that there are witnesses present. Yeah, just
well the point is is there's more direct evidence and you're claiming
there's more direct evidence even though you could win without it, do
we demand that that evidence be brought to us before we פסקן
pasken the case? So it makes a lot of sense to say
we're going to make that demand. The question is is what are
we going to say בדיעבד bedieved when you're not able to produce
it? If you want another irony, by the way, רשב״ם Rashbam points
out that according to another גמרא Gemara if I say ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon saw me pay David there back and ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon come to the court and they say, "Yeah, we
were with Dov and David at the ballgame, we never saw him
pay David any any loan back," so you would think that then
I should lose the case, right? The הלכה halacha actually is, but
remember I would have won just by claiming I paid you back.
But I said ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon saw it, they came
and they said we didn't see it. So actually in a different
גמרא Gemara the פסק psak is is that I still win because
we figure like who knows, they weren't paying attention, you know, nobody
asked them to serve as witnesses or whatever. If I said I
designated ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon as witnesses to see me pay
you back the loan and we brought ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
in and they said no it never happened, then clearly I would
lose. But if I said, "Yeah, we were all at the ballgame
together, I paid David back his loan," and the court says, "Was
there anybody else around who could testify to that?" I say, "Yeah,
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon they were there with us in the
seats right there," and they come and they say, "Yeah, we never
saw it." So what does "we never saw it" mean? Does it
mean I'm lying or does it mean they weren't paying attention? So
there's actually another גמרא Gemara that says it means, you know, we'll
say they weren't paying attention. So now it's like doubly ironic. I
say ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon were there, but even and we're
saying I can't win the case until I bring ראובן Reuven and
שמעון. Shimon. But if I bring ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and
they say they didn't see it, I still win. But if I
don't bring ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, we still need them to
come, you know, so it makes it very strange because who knows,
who knows what they'll say, you know, let's just get all the
information in front of us. But it becomes very strange. תוספות Tosafot
actually asks: so do you mean to tell me according to the
רשב״ם Rashbam who says that בדיעבד bedieved it won't work, if you
don't produce ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon you lose, but if you
produce ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and they contradict what you said
and they said they never saw you... don't contradict, they didn't say
they saw you not pay it back, but they say they never
saw you pay it back, then you're going to win? Right? It's
it becomes very strange. So anyway, so those are some open questions.
Yes? So what does this say about a verbal contract? Is there
any conclusion in terms of like are verbal contracts always going to
be invalid or not? I don't know what this has to do
with a verbal contract. Well because in other words this last case
it was a verbal... No it wasn't a verbal contract, it was
lending money without that's not a contract, it was lending money without
the presence of witnesses, okay, or without the presence of a שטר.
shtar. Okay. Well that would be a contract. The contract is that...
yeah exactly. Okay, all right, so let's take a look now next
משנה: mishna: מי שפרע מקצת חובו, Mi shepara miktzat chovo, somebody paid
off part of the debt. So in the previous משנה mishna the
way we dealt with it was that we have a third party
hold on to the שטר shtar and I said if I don't
pay it off by a certain date give the שטר shtar back
to the original owner, you know, I'll pay back in full. But
here we're going to do what you normally would do is you
want to have evidence that the שטר shtar that the debt was
partly paid. So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda אומר omer יחליף, yachlif, produce
a substitute שטר. shtar. It said I owed David $1,000, I paid
him $200, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says write a new שטר shtar
that says I owe him 800. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi אומר omer
יכתוב שובר, yichtov shover, no, write a write a receipt that I
basically now have a receipt that I paid 200. אמר רבי יהודה,
Amar Rebbi Yehuda, said רבי יהודה: Rebbi Yehuda: נמצא זה צריך להיות
שומר שוברו מן העכברים, Nimtza zeh tzarich lihiot shomer shovro min ha'achbarim,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says that's not fair because If I lose
my receipt or the rats get to it, I'm going to have
to pay David the full thousand dollars. It's rather than having a
שטר shtar that says a thousand and a receipt that says 200,
which now could lead to the loss of the receipt and paying
the full thousand, just replace the thousand dollar שטר shtar with an
800 dollar שטר. shtar. Yeah, the עכברים achbarim could eat that too,
I guess. Right, but he would have had to watch his שטר
shtar regardless. Why create now a new responsibility to watch a שטר
shtar that could lead to a, you know, to a to a
wrong, a ruling? Right, now there's two people who could lose their
שטר. shtar. Okay. So אמר ליה amar lei רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose,
so רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose said כך יפה לו. kach yafe lo.
Fine, that's good, let him worry about that, you know, ולא יירע
כוחו של זה. velo yeira kocho shel zeh. Why should we hurt
David's standing? Now, how does an 800 dollar שטר shtar hurt David's
standing? I only owe him 800 dollars, okay? So why shouldn't we...
so he says, yes, I know that if we give Dov the
200 dollar receipt he might lose it and then he'll wind
up paying a, you know,
that 200 dollars again. But that's better than hurting David here and
changing a thousand dollar שטר shtar to an 800. How does it
hurt him? I tell you. Okay. Yeah, I can't say exactly but
I have a feeling about it. It's like he only paid part
back. Right. So put some of the burden of responsibility on your...
like why should I lose...? Right, that's true. Okay, that could be.
That could be. But again, David is going to have to watch
the שטר shtar regardless. So, so who's losing out by having...? So
the simple sense is, and that's what this large תוספות Tosafot discusses,
the simple sense here of the position of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is that we write a new
שטר shtar as of today's date. So if I borrowed a thousand
dollars a year ago and we replace it with an 800 dollar
שטר shtar dated today, I'm only going to have lien, David's only
going to have liens for the remaining 800 dollars, he's only going
to have liens on stuff I own as of today forward, right?
But he wants his liens from a year ago when he lent
the שטר. shtar. So he really loses out a lot there to
replace it with an 800 dollar שטר shtar dated today. He loses
out all of his liens for the year ago. Okay, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב הונא אמר רב,
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav, אין הלכה לא כרבי יהודה ולא כרבי
יוסי. ein halacha lo k'Rebbe Yehuda velo k'Rebbe Yose. We don't rule
like רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda or רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yose. אלא, Ella,
what we... here's how we rule. בית דין מקרעין השטר, Beis Din
mekrin hashtar, the בית דין Beis Din tears up the original שטר,
shtar, וכותבין לו שטר אחר מזמן ראשון. vekotvin lo shtar acher mizman
rishon. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot says what's underlined here is the words
מזמן ראשון. mizman rishon. We're... it's basically ruling like רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda, but the substitute שטר shtar is the original date. Okay? So
David doesn't lose any of his lien. It's... it's dated from a
year ago. All right, that makes a lot of sense. As if
he lent 800. Right, that makes a lot of sense. As if
he lent 800. So אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב הונא ואמרי ליה
רב ירמיה בר אבא לרב הונא, amar lei Rav Nachman leRav Huna
ve'amrei lei Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba leRav Huna, שמיע ליה לרב הא
ברייתא? shmieh lei leRav ha baraita? If Rav who said we don't
rule like the משנה, Mishnah, we rule that the בית דין Beis
Din does it from the original date, if he had heard the
following ברייתא, baraita, דתניא, detanya, we're going to... what's the ברייתא baraita
going to say? עדים מקרעין את השטר וכותבין לו שטר אחר מזמן
ראשון. Eidim mekrin es hashtar vekotvin lo shtar acher mizman rishon. There's
another ברייתא baraita that says in the name of רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda and clarifies that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda meant not of today's
date. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda meant exactly what you, Rav, said. רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said you tear it up and you write it
as of the earlier date. So if you had heard that ברייתא,
baraita, that would have clarified for you רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda's position.
הוה הדר ביה, Hava hadar beih, you would have reversed yourself. Not
meaning reversed your position, but you wouldn't have had to get up
on a soapbox and say we don't rule like this משנה, Mishnah,
we rule from the earlier date. There's a ברייתא baraita that makes
it clear that that's רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda's position, that יחליף yachalif
means the earlier date. Of course, then it's not clear why he
says that it's hurting the guy, okay? But Rav under... that's what
תוספות Tosafot says, Rav understood that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda meant as
of today's date because the end of the משנה Mishnah says that
it's hurting... it's hurting the creditor. But anyway, but here we're saying,
nope, a ברייתא baraita clarifies that even according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda, he says exactly what you just said, that it means as
of the earlier date and it's not hurting the creditor. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him: שמיע ליה, shmieh
lei, Rav knows about that ברייתא. baraita. And nevertheless he had פסקן
paskan the way he did, he had to פסקן paskan that he
was saying something different. Why? What was he saying that was different
than the ברייתא? baraita? He's basically saying רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and
of the earlier date. So ולא הדר ביה, velo hadar beih, he
didn't retract his statement. Why? בשלמא בית דינא אלימי לאפקועי ממונא. Bishlama
Beis Dina alimei l'afkuei mamona. The question... the issue now is now
what we're underlining is not the words מזמן ראשון, mizman rishon, but
we're underlining the words בית דין. Beis Din. Because the ברייתא baraita
said the עדים eidim tear it up and rewrite the שטר shtar
of the earlier date. And Rav is saying the בית דין Beis
Din tears it up. You need the בית דין Beis Din to
create a new שטר shtar of the earlier date. בשלמא בית דינא
אלימי לאפקועי ממונא, Bishlama Beis Dina alimei l'afkuei mamona, they have the
power, they can say הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker Beis Din hefker,
so they can create new, you know, economic, you know, financial realities.
אלא עדים שעשו שליחותן חוזרים ועושים שליחותן? Ella eidim she'asu shlichusan chozrim
ve'osim shlichusan? But after the עדים eidim have signed the original שטר,
shtar, how could they be authorized to write a new שטר shtar
of 800 once you tear up the שטר shtar of the thousand?
So we'll continue with this tomorrow. I don't want to fully unpack
this, but basically now what we said is the idea there's one
question of כותב שובר. Kosev Shovar. Do you create a new responsibility
on the borrower to watch his שובר? shovar? But if you're not
כותב שובר, Kosev Shovar, your alternative for a partly paid document is
to replace it. So and replace it with the new amount. And
then the question is two questions: from today's date or from the
earlier date? From today's date is very easy. Right, why is it
easy to do a new document from today's date? Because the same
way I could write now borrow $800 from David and then we
would create a document that said I borrowed 800. We could tear
up the $1,000 document and write a document that I owe $800
as of today. That's an easy thing to do, doing it as
of today. The question is how can we create a new document
that creates liens from before? So a, does Rabbi Yehuda say when
he says you replace it, you replace it with today's date or
the past date? And b, if he's saying the past date, that's
a big חידוש chiddush that you can pre-date it. Okay? And if
you're doing that, can that be done with the עדים edim themselves
or do you need the בית דין, beis din, the power of
a בית דין beis din to create that type of a שטר?
shtar? Okay, and that's now Rav's חידוש chiddush is not to say
that we're, you know, that we're lenient or whatever, you know, that
we flex our muscles by doing it earlier, that's the ברייתא braisa
says as well. Rav is actually saying is limiting that and saying
if you're going to do that or when you're going to do
that, you're going to need a בית דין beis din to do
it. It can't be done just by עדים. edim. Okay, and so
we'll explore this issue tomorrow. And this is Rav's חידוש. chiddush.